so Ubuntu several years ago I underwent
an abortion
and although I've since grown and
improved as a person the burden of my
past decision
still lingers accompanied by the fear of
potential consequences
Strangely I don't mind this lingering
guilt as it serves as a constant
reminder of my past mistakes and my
commitment to not repeat them
I hold the belief that abortion is wrong
even though I am uncertain about the
consciousness of the baby slash fetus
at that particular point
my guilt stems from knowing that I might
have destroyed a life
do you think my feelings of Shame and
guilt are Justified I believe they are
yeah absolutely yeah yeah and it's good
that the person is not denying them
the person is not denying them
and is actually using them as a context
to not make the same mistake yeah
definitely as for the consequences well
yeah consequences of taking life have to be
consequences of taking life have to be
experienced
[Music] um
um
at some point now how much those karmic
consequences would be experienced well
you can see from the suitors that if
somebody say has taken human life and then
say has taken human life and then
afterwards
they made the tremendous effort and developed
made the tremendous effort and developed
their mind free the Mind from greed
aversion delusion or at least partially
those consequences would diminish
or in other words the the consequences
that they will have to experience would
be fairly miniscule in comparison to
what they would have experienced if
their mind were not rightly developed
and when I say Riley developed I don't
mean you go and sit on a 10-day nostril
watching retreat
I mean you fully start accepting
responsibility for your actions training
your mind to remain unmoved in face of
hindrances not feeling greed not feeling
Vision not fueling the wrong views
so getting the right View
is your kind of safety card if you can
become a sotopana it should be your
basically your your efforts to name it
that or more even better but at least that
or more even better but at least that
because it said that the surabana cannot
be
reborn lower than a human realm
regardless of the actions and
consequences that are waiting for them
from they did before
what I like about this uh this question
where this person seems to be is is
keeping um
um
we're not trying to find
is the baby was the baby that have
Consciousness at the point of abortion
or did it not when does the
Consciousness arrive
she's not trying to get rid of her guilt
she's actually finding value in it
yeah well she's recognizing that
regardless of the answer
that you might get depending on whom you
ask basically
from her point of view from her
individual point of view what comes first is the
point of view what comes first is the
guilt and the always lingering doubt
that it could have been a life
that you have taken so it doesn't matter
what science or religion gives you is an
answer yes he was no it wasn't the fact
is that act in and of itself from her
point of view will always remain
doubtful because you you cannot verify
like scientifically if somebody tells
you no there isn't well it's a it's a
presupposition basically no it's not
conscious somebody said no fetus is
conscious again that they can't verify
that either but the fact that it could
be is more than enough for you to
recognize that actually yeah so um
killing it should not have been done in
that sense
so even if fetus is unconscious it's
still a human fetus
so from its point of conception to the
point of death it's a human entity in
that sense at different stages
you can say it's a clump of cells yes
but it's a clump of cells of a very
different value
it's a clamp of cells from which all the
other cells develop so it's not the same
to says you know my nails are a clump of
cells yeah and now
and the fetus is a clump of cells
they're of a very different order for
very different potential
so even if fetus is completely not
conscious it's still a human fetus
it's not a squirrel fetus
and that can never change
and that's what I mean regardless of
what answer you might find
fundamentally that's something you
cannot deny and because of that if
you're honest you will experience guilt
if that's the action that you did
and you can't undo it
so people say you're going to make Merit
and yeah that's all good that's all fine
but Merit will result in good
consequences later on but that has
nothing to do with the bad stuff you
can't offset that you can just add more
of good things that you experience sure
but what can actually offset your bad
actions including killing and so on uh
even if you did it out of ignorance and
like not premeditated murder type of
thing but still is if you develop your
mind towards nibana rightly if you
abandon the wrong views if you overcome
sensuality factually as the Buddha did
say to angulimala like the consequences
he was experiencing while he was still
alive and people throwing stones at him
and so on he says oh bear it Brahmin
that's that's that's all of the
consequences that are left for you
although you know he killed so many
people before
if he were not to become another hunt he
would have been burning in Hell's for
eons and eons
so there were still consequences of his
actions but they became they couldn't
pass that immediate level while this
body was still present that's it that
was the extent of them
so it's like the doing making good
doing other good actions to try and
offset the bad that you've done in the
past doesn't you know it doesn't really
work as you're saying it's the uprooting
or the thing that made you do that wrong
exactly exactly that's the point that's
the difference yeah so what were the
roots what are the roots of any
unwholesome action killing lying
cheating stealing all these precepts
that we talk about what is a Common
Thread to all of them
if you abandon that if you if you
practice aims it up rooting those roots
of those actions then even things that
you did in the past will not actually
pertain to you anymore
and and those roots are basically what
we talk about desire
ill will
inauthenticity lack of self-transparency
lack of taking up responsibility
so if you actually from 10 onwards
start practicing
towards abandoning desire towards
restraining desire towards not
proliferating desire
abandoning acting out of ill will not
giving in to kind of Acts that would
distract you from yourself in a sense of
bearing the responsibility the weight of
your existence and all of that
you are actually uncovering and getting
closer to like what the uh the true practice of
to like what the uh the true practice of
Dharma is and that in and of itself is
developing your mind
so then even even any consequences they
might be waiting for you if your mind is
truly developed through first accepting
the weight of your actions as we often
say the weight of responsibility every
day not once so it goes away whenever it
comes back I'm there waiting for it
that cannot change
and anything I do will not be rooted in
trying to get rid of it because that
means I don't want responsibility for
something I've actually did
so that's something like if somebody
already has that attitude that they're
using that practically to to keep their
context that's that's extremely good
now on top of that I don't know about
their understanding of dama is but yeah
sure make Merit be generous help others
but really focus on uprooting the desire
uprooting the conceit uprooting the
craving greed diversion delusion and then you
greed diversion delusion and then you
won't have to worry even about
because who knows we all might have done
even worse things in our previous life
that still haven't been experienced yet
and they're the consequences of those
things are waiting for us
so even if no if you haven't
performed an abortion had an abortion
performed uh in this life or anything
like that you might have done other
things worse things beforehand than
those those consequences are waiting for
you so you shouldn't feel safe for as
long as you're in samsara basically
that's what I'm saying because many
people can accept and come to terms with
what they did but then what do you do
next you just go back to life and
sensuality and proliferation and sexual
intercourses and everything else or do
you no no I'll carry on this now and
approve this desire even further
so then the consequences
of my actions now that I can remember
and even more that I probably can't
remember cannot touch me
cannot touch me
so in other words use it not just to
temporarily deal with this specific thing from the
deal with this specific thing from the
past that you felt guilty or shameful
but accept it use it and then aim it at
the wholesome Sarah basically
abandon the whole thing because that's
the only true safety
because factually there are consequences
of your actions whether you accept it
come to terms with it that's fine that
can obviously help your well-being Here
and Now but that does not change the
fact that uh you killed and the
consequences will have to be experienced
so it's useful to not forget that as
well